In the previous lesson, I introduced JavaScript which we're going to use to
generate dynamic content within our web pages.
Now JavaScripts, like many other programming languages,
has things like variables and arrays and objects, loops, conditionals, and
functions that we're going to see in the next few lessons.
Now I'm going to assume that you've seen some programming language before,
maybe Java, Python, C, something like that.
But even if you know those languages,
there are some important differences with Java Script.
In particular, the relationship between functions and objects and how they're
defined and then, later, of course, how the JavaScript interacts with the HTML.
Let's start with the basics of how we define a variable in JavaScript.
In JavaScript, we use the keyword var or var, V-A-R, to indicate that we're
declaring a variable, then the name of the variable, optionally, some initial value.
Here I've declared a variable called age and I set it equal to 22.
I can have a variable hold a string.
Here are the string Jane Doe is the name, or
it can have a boolean value false for this variable here.
Once I've declared a variable, how do I see it's value?
Well, if we're doing this in the context of a web browser, a webpage,
there are four different ways we can do that.
The first way we'll see is if we're using the script element, or the script tag,
within the HTML, is to write the variable directly into the webpage.
We can do that using document.write, which we saw in the lesson last time.
Here we're using the script tag, we declare a variable called age set it equal
to 12, and we use document.write.
We pass it the variable, and this will print the value 12 within the html page.
It's important to note that this approach is somewhat discouraged.
We're clearly combining the content and
the functionality, the html and the JavaScript together,
we'll see better alternatives later in this week in the course.
The second way of seeing the variable's value
is writing it to the log within the console within the browser.
For instance in this case, again I have the script tags,
I set a variable called age = 12 and I used console.log.
I pass up the variable, and it'll print that value in the log file in the console.
In a browser like Chrome, it would look something like this, here's the value 12.
A third way is to use the alert function.
This will create a pop up with that variable's value
at the top of the browser.
So again, embedding the JavaScript in the HTML page,
creating the variable called age and using the alert function.
And at the top of my web browser page I would see this page says 12.
Last, I can use what's known as the REPL, that's a read evaluate print loop,
which is in the console and
I just have to type the name of the variable and it'll print out it's value.
Here I have the variable called age once again.
And I just type age and then REPL will print out it's value in print out, 12.
Now when I first started talking about variables I gave some examples of
variables.
We had a number, a string and a boolean value but
I didn't declare any sort of type, I just said they were variables.
That's because in JavaScript, we can change the type of a variable.
In this case, we see a variable called id, which is set to 33.2,
a floating point number.
And then I can change id to the string secret.
That is I can change id from a number to a string.
In JavaScript there are five primitive types.
If I have a variable of one type, I can simply change it to that of another.
The first is a number as we've seen.
We can have an integer, floating point number.
We can also have positive and negative infinity or not a number.
We'll see a little bit more of this on the next slide.
We can have strings, booleans, which are, of course, true and false.
There's a representation of null, meaning it has no value, an empty value.
But there's also undefined, which is JavaScript's way of saying,
I have not seen this before, I don't have any value for it.
Let's look at numbers first.
JavaScript numbers, whether they're a floating point number or an integer,
are stored internally using floating point notation.
As mentioned, there's a positive and negative infinity values,
which represent enormously positive and enormously negative numbers.
And then, there's not a number, NaN.
If, for instance, we can try to convert, say, the string tree to a number,
this would return NaN, to indicate that it's not a number.
As in many other programming languages, we can use basic arithmetic operations,
plus, minus, times, divide, mod on JavaScript numbers.
These follow the standard multiply, divide, add, subtract precedence rules.
And there's also post-increment, ++ and
post-decrement - -, Here on the bottom, we see some examples of using
arithmetic operators on number, numeric variables.
Here we see post increments minus and then following the order of operations,
the precedence rules for doing multiple operations.
The second type of variable that we have in JavaScript are strings
As in many other programming languages, strings are represented using a series of
characters which are under the cover, under the hood, just numbers.
In JavaScript you'll often see single quotes around strings.
For instance, in this case,
'I am a dolphin', just have single quotes around it.
However, we used double quotes if the string, itself,
contains a single quote, for instance," I'm a dolphin".
We can use backslash characters as escape characters,
as in many other programming languages.
\n for newline, \t for tab,
\\ if we want the character backslash to appear in the text.
And it's important to note, and
we'll keep coming back to this, that JavaScript strings are immutable.
We can change its string, but that would just return a new string.
But once we set the string, we cannot change it.
Some common functions on strings include concatenating or
adding two strings together.
In the example at the bottom, we see firstName is John, lastName is doe.
And I can use the concat function to concatenate
the first name with this empty space and then the last name variable.
This will produce this string, John doe,
which I will store in this variable, fullName.
I can also use the string + string notation, which will still do
concatenation and now greeting is going to say, HELLO, John doe.
Strings also provide functions such as to uppercase and
to lowercase, these will change the case of each character in the string.
Again, keep in mind, it's not changing the string,
it's returning a new string that's been converted.
For instance, in this case, to uppercase will return this string.
It doesn't change greeting.
It's just a new string with the same characters, but now all uppercase.
Last, strings have a property called length, which will return the length
of the string of number of characters in the string, as we can see down here.
So far we've seen numbers and
we've seen strings, let's see the other three primitive variable types.
Booleans are logical values that can only be true and false.
Just like in other programming languages.
Now, one feature of JavaScript is that we can use any value as a boolean, for
instance when doing conditional operators.
Only true is true, and only false is false.
But in JavaScript there's a notion of truthy and falsy values.
It's probably easier just to remember the false-y ones, which are things like null,
undefined, 0, NaN, or an empty string.
These are not false because they're not booleans, but
they're rather treated as false in conditional operators.
Just about everything else is a truth-y value, for instance, the string cow.
Even the string, false, is a truthy value because it's a string,
it's a non empty string, numbers like 5, even negative numbers, etc.
The last two variable types are null and undefined.
Null is just used to represent no value or an empty value.
In this case, we see that null is part of the declaration of this variable.
On the other hand, undefined means it doesn't have any value assigned to it yet.
Here, we can see that for salary,
there's no value assigned in its initialization or declaration.
So that when we go and try to print it, this is a valid variable but
it doesn't have a value yet and it would be considered undefined.
To summarize, we've started to look at JavaScript variables and there are five
primitive variable types, number, string, boolean, null and undefined.
In the next few lessons, we'll start looking at how we use these variables in
order to write our JavaScript programs.