Last time we saw the five primitive variable types in JavaScript.
But each of those only allows us to hold one value.
Sometimes we want to have a collection of values.
Maybe we want them in some particular order.
Maybe we want a collection of key value pairs that are associated or
combined into something semantically meaningful.
In this lesson, we'll see how to address those two concerns using arrays and
objects.
As in many other programming language, JavaScript has a notion of an array.
An array is used to store a list of values in a single variable.
But unlike many other programming languages,
within the array the values don't have to be all the same type.
In this case we've declared a variable called my array that contains three
elements, a string called cars, a number 12 and a Boolean value false.
I can access individual elements of the array using the standard
array notation in this case I can get element number one
using a zero based index and that will return the value 12.
I can also set element number two of the array, again using the zero based index,
for instance I can set element number two to the value true.
Now it's worth pointing out here, that in this case I got a number, in this case
I used a boolean, but I'm able to change the type, of the element in the array,
just like I'm able to change the type of any variable in JavaScript.
Last, if I wanna know how many elements are in the array,
I can use its length property in this case, it would return three.
Now in many other programming languages,
you have to be careful about how you use the indices to the array.
If you use an index that's too big, you might get an exception, or
you might overwrite some other data.
If you use an index that's negative, you might again, get some unexpected behavior.
In JavaScript, when I'm reading an array by the index, and
I use an index that's out of bounds, that's negative or
greater than the size, then what I will get back, is undefined.
In this example I have three elements in my array.
When I try to print element number 4, remember these are zero-based indices.
So 0, 1, 2.
There is no element number 4.
I would just get back undefined.
And in this case, when I try to access element number negative 9 Again,
we'll just get back undefined.
No error,
no exception, nothing like that, just JavaScript saying, there's no value there.
Now the rules for writing are slightly different.
If I'm writing to an array, and the index is out of bounds, it will,
in fact, add it to the array.
Here we have an array, again, of three elements, cat, dog and banana.
These are zero based indices, so 0, 1, 2.
When I try to access element number four but I'm writing to it,
I'm not reading it, I'm writing it, I'm setting it to panda.
It actually will add it to the array.
And if I go and ask for element number 4, then I will get back panda.
But what about element number 3?
Well, there is no element number 3, it doesn't put any value there.
It's still undefined.
Now, if the index is negative, we'll still have a mapping.
From that index even though it's a negative number to that element.
In this case, I'm setting element -5 to elephant.
And when I print element -5, it will still remember that -5 is mapped to,
if you will, the string elephant.
How many elements are now in a?
It's 5.
It's the three that we originally had, cat, dog and banana.
Plus the two that we added in this example, panda and elephant.
When I use console.log and
pass at the array, it prints the first three elements as we expected.
It points out that here at element number three it's undefined that times one,
means there's one undefined element here.
Here's element number 4, and then at the end it's reminding us or
pointing out that there's this mapping of element -5 to the string elephant.
So this should demonstrate to you that we're able to add and remove elements to
an array, it's not fixed length like in many other programming languages.
But we can instead think of it as some sort of list that's growing and
shrinking dynamically.
In an array, if we want to add elements we can either use the push or
unshift functions.
Here's an array with two elements, car and bike.
And I can use push, in this case,
pushing scooter this will add the element to the end of the array.
Now if you're familiar with data structures you should know that push is
the stack operation and we can think of the end of the array as a stack.
We can push elements to it.
Now if we print out myArray we'll see that it has car, bike, and scooter.
I can add something to the front of the array, to the beginning of the array,
using the function unshift.
Unshift just allows us to put something at the front of the array.
Here we're putting train at the front of the array.
And now the array contains the four elements, train, car, bike, and scooter.
In the same way that we can add and remove elements from the rear, or the end of
the array, or the front, or the beginning of the array we can also remove them.
This is the array from before.
And I mentioned in the previous slide that the back of the array,
the rear or the tail of the array, we can think of as a stack.
If I can push things to add them, then I pop them to remove them.
Pop will return and remove that last element.
Now vehicle will become scooter because that's the last element of the array,
and that element has been removed.
I guess I think of shifting in terms of removing something from the beginning of
the arrays,
shifting everything over to the left and whatever was at the front falls off.
Now vehicle is whatever was the first element of the array, which is train, and
myArray still contains only car and bike.
So we've seen how we can collect variables into a single variable, known as an array.
An array does not have to have all the variables of the same type.
And we can add elements and remove elements from the front and the rear.
And we can even use indices that in other programming languages
would be considered out of bounds.
But what if we want to have a collection of associated variables and
values, but not necessarily keep them in an array.
But have semantically meaningful names for them In that case we would use objects.
JavaScript objects are used to store key value pairs.
And just as with arrays, values can be of any type, and
a value of a JavaScript object can be an array or an object itself.
We consider these values as properties and we can access them using the .property,
the name of the property, or the array notation with the property as a string.
In this case we're creating a variable named person, but
we're using this object notation with the open and close curly braces.
Now we have a key value pair which is the property name and
it's value which is the string John Doe.
Now it's important to remember that what we're creating here is an object,
if you are familiar with object oriented programming languages.
We're not creating a class here, we're not saying these are its fields but
rather, we're saying these are the key value pairs.
And I have to admit that I often accidentally put a semicolon here but
what you need here is a comma to indicate that this is a list or
a collection of key value pairs, a property, colon, and then it's value.
The next property will be age.
It's value is 25.
We can have a property ismale with the value true.
Here we have the property personality, which is an array of three elements,
an array of three strings.
And last, we have the property of this object, which is, itself, an object.
The property is named company, that property has two properties, name and ID.
If I want to access in this person object,
its name attribute or its name property, I just use the name of the variable,
dot the name of the property, now it returns value which is 25.
I can also get a property using the sort of array notation
with the name of the property as a string.
So company is a string.
But this will return person.company, which is this object here.
It'll get its ID property and that's this number here.
Now if you're familiar with object oriented programming you generally know
that when I create the class, I say, these are the properties, the fields, or
attributes.
Then that's it, I can't add any more fields or properties or
attributes to that class.
However, in JavaScript, the object, we can almost think of as an array,
in that we can keep adding things to it.
And we can even add new properties after we've initialized it.
In this example, I have a variable called pet.
It's an object.
It has a field called name, set to Cooper, and a field type, which is set to dog.
Down here, I try to access its age.
Well, pet does not have an age, so this would just return undefined.
But in the next line, I set the age to 11.
Now you note up here that there is no age property in this object so
this will add that age property to the object.
And now if I print it the age is 11.
Likewise I can even do this using the array notation with the property name as
a string.
I'm adding the property called status using it as a string in this array
notation.
I'm setting it to be good boy, and when I print it, I get good boy.
In summary, we've seen how we can collect variables together in arrays and objects.
In arrays the elements are stored in an ordered sense but
in objects we use key value pairs, and we can even add new key value pairs,
new properties to the objects after we've created them.