Up until now, we've been looking at the core JavaScript features, variables,
arrays, objects, and conditional statements.
The last sort of core feature of the language that we need to look at
before we start seeing how to apply it to web development is functions.
Like most other programming languages,
JavaScript supports the definition of functions here using the keyword function,
followed by the name of the function, and in the parameter list.
Now remember in JavaScript, variables are declared using simply the keyword, var.
We don't need to declare their type when we declare them, so
we just have the name of the variable.
The body of the function is delineated with the curly braces,
and then we have the code itself within the function.
In this case, we're computing the factorial of n using a for loop.
We can return a value from the function using the return keyword.
Here, we're returning the product that we've computed,
which holds the factorial value.
In the code that's using this function, we've got some variable x.
We pass x to the factorial function that returns a variable that will store in f.
And we can print the value of f.
Now we saw arrays in a previous lesson, and
one of the nice things about JavaScript is the ability to apply a function
to each element in the array without having to write our own loops around it.
Here we have an example, where I have an array called nums which has four numbers,
and then I have a function called print.
Print takes a number or a variable n, and just writes it to the the console.
I can use the nums for each function and
pass the name of the function to forEach,
that is nums is my variable from up here.
That variable, which is an array, has an associated function called forEach.
And then, what I pass is not a value,
as in an argument to a function, but rather than name of this function, and
what this will do is apply this function, which is, print.
To each element in the array thereby printing or
writing to the console's log each element.
Here's another example.
I've created a function called isEven.
It takes a value n and returns true if n mod 2 equals 0,
meaning when I divide it, the remainder by 2 the remainder is 0.
That means it's even. I can use and erase every function to
determine if isEven returns true for every element in that array.
That is nums again is the name of my array.
Arrays have an associated function called every that will call
this function, up here, on every element of the array and
return true, if this function returns true for every element.
In this case, because the numbers are all even, isEven will return true for
each of those four elements, therefore every will return true.
If I had an odd number in my array, isEven would return false for that element.
So every would return false, because this is not true for every element.
There's an associated function called some, S-O-M-E,
that will return true if this is true for any or for some elements in the array.
Last, in the same way that forEach
will apply the function to each element in the array.
I might want to apply that function but then do something with the return value.
So here I have a function called, square, which will square the number,
multiply it by itself.
I'm going to, on my array, invoke the map function.
So arrays have a function called map that takes another function and
applies it to every element of the array.
But then returns a new array which holds the values
that are the results of applying that function to each element of the array.
In this case,
squares would be this array here to hold the squares of the values up here.
One of the complicated features of any programming language is knowing what
will happen to a value when you pass it as an argument to some function.
If that function tries to change the argument, what will happen to it?
In JavaScript, primitive arguments, numbers, boolean, strings, etc,
are passed by value, that means that the function cannot change them.
Here I have a function called try to change which takes an input x and
it sets x to four.
Outside the function I declare a variable y, set it to 11, and
I pass y to the tryToChange function.
As you know at this point, x holds the value of y.
And when it tries to change it to four, the question is,
does it actually change y to four?
And the answer is no,
y does not change because y is a primitive variable, it's a number.
It's passed by value meaning that the value is set to x.
But it does not change when I change it within the function.
On the other hand, when a variable is an object, those are passed by reference.
And that means that if they're changed in the function the object itself
does get changed.
Now I have a function called changeMe,
which is going to increment the age property of that object.
I create a variable outside of the function called p.
It has an age property which is set to 30.
When I pass p to changeMe, object becomes a reference to p if you will.
And when I do obj.age++, incrementing the age property of the object,
I'm actually incrementing the age property of p.
So that when I print p.age, now it's 31.
JavaScript functions are objects, that means that the functions
can take advantage of the benefits of an object, such as having properties.
They're not shown in this lesson.
A function has for instance, a property called arguments that it can use to access
all of the arguments that are passed to it as an array.
But since JavaScript functions are objects,
that means we can have a variable that holds that function.
For instance in this example, I have a variable called add.
And it's value is not a primitive value and
it's not an object using the notation we saw before, but
rather it's a function which takes two inputs, a and b, and returns their sum.
That means I can invoke this function
using the name of the variable that holds it, in this case add.
And I can invoke it using three and five, for instance.
There are a lot of benefits of that feature, and
one of them is that I can have a function as part of an object.
That is, I can have a function be a property of some other object.
In this case, I have a variable called johnDoe, which is an object.
And one of its properties is greeting, which is a function.
When this function is invoked, it'll just return the string, Hello,
Nice Meeting You.
So that when I invoke it, using the name of the object and
the name of it's property as a function, it'll invoke this method,
it'll return that string, and that's what would get logged to the console.
Now we're gonna get too much into JavaScript object oriented programming.
But it's worth pointing out that all objects in JavaScript
have what's known as a prototype.
The prototype is just the basic set of properties
that it has from which it can inherit.
This prototype is itself a property named __proto___, as you can see here.
That proto property is also an object, it has a proto property and so on,
and there is a root of all the objects, a root prototype Object.prototype.
We can use this in order to create objects
that inherit the properties of other objects and so on.
In this example, we're going to see a function that's going to be
used as a prototype for creating other objects.
We can think of this as a class definition,
though it's not exactly the same.
For instance, I have a function, we've seen this before, this notation,
function, the name of the function, and then the list of its parameters.
But you see within the function,
we're setting the properties of an object called, this.
This refers to this object, this current object.
And here, I'm setting the object's name, age and greeting.
Down here, I can use this prototype to create a new object using the new keyword.
And if you've seen programming languages like, Java, C++,
etc, you're familiar with this.
Where here, person is the name of the prototypes or class if you will, but
not exactly the same.
But we'll consider that the prototype, it will invoke that function,
it'll pass John Doe and 32, to name an age.
But what will return is an object where its name age and
greeting properties have been set.
So using the keyword new, I can invoke that function and then what comes back
is a new object, and I can set John Doe to hold that object.
Now when I invoke johnDoe.greeting, it'll invoke this method.
And as in many other programming languages, when the method refers to this
.name, it means this object's name, this object's name had been set to John Doe.
And that's why it prints, hello, my name is John Doe.
I can then use that prototype to create another object, this time Jane Doe.
Jane Doe has her own name of course, in that separate object.
And so when it prints the greeting, it'll print a return, hello,
my name is Jane Doe.
We can use prototypes in the same way that we might use inheritance in
object oriented programming languages like Java and C++.
Here, we'll create another prototype called students and
we set its prototype to a person from the previous slide.
So in this case, we can think of student extending person
using person as its prototype or inheriting all of its properties.
But student can have its own properties for instance, school.
When I create a variable called Sarah Brown,
we're gonna use the student prototype here.
It'll pass, these three arguments to this function, but
name and age, are passed to the person prototype.
The prototype of this student, is that person object,
of course it's gonna set the school, it's inherited, if you will,
the properties of the person, including the greeting function.
And we can also use the keyword instanceof to see,
does this variable extend, or if you will, this particular prototype.
Sarah Brown is a student, a student is a person.
Last, in the same way that we could add properties to a object,
we can also add properties to a prototype.
And we can change the underlying prototype implementation in our code.
Here we just have a person again, person has a name, age and occupation,
but to its prototype, we can add the property planet,
and we can also add the property introduction, which is a function.
So now when I create a person using that prototype, it's not simply what's up here
but also this object now has a planet property because we changed the prototype.
And it has an introduction function again because we changed the prototype.
To summarize, in this lesson, we've been talking about JavaScript functions.
Like many other programming languages,
JavaScript lets the programmer define functions.
But in JavaScript, functions are objects and functions can be used in objects.
Functions can be used to create objects.
And we can use function prototypes to create blueprints for
creating other objects as well.